A Guide to the Department of History: Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr. Papers, 1950-1983: UA 0037
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Department of History: Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr. Papers
1950-1983
Special Collections, James Madison University
Dingledine, Raymond J., Jr., Dr.
UA 0037
1.2 cubic feet; 3 boxes
This collection is comprised of the professional and academic papers of Dr. Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr., a professor of Social Studies and History at James Madison University (formerly Madison College), and correspondence and research materials for the book, "Madison College: the First Fifty Years, 1908-1958," published in 1959.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Parts of the collection are closed due to FERPA restrictions. Until the restriction is lifted, the materials will be housed in the collection control file. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated by Raymond C. Dingledine in April 1984.
Bio/Historical Note
Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr. was born in 1919 to Raymond Carlyle Dingledine and Agness Browne Stribling Dingledine. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Virginia, and in 1948, began teaching at Madison College in the Social Sciences and History Department. He became head of the History Department in 1965 when it separated from the Social Sciences, a position he held until his retirement in 1984. In 1959 he published, "Madison College: the First Fifty Years, 1908-1956." Dingledine was married to Emily Reel. He died in 1990. Dingledine's father, Raymond Sr. taught at the State Normal School from 1913 until his death in 1941. His mother, Agness graduated from the State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg in 1915, and later served as House Mother and as Alumni Secretary at Madison College. Dingledine Hall is named in her honor.
Scope and Content
The Department of History: Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr., Papers are comprised of committee papers, meeting minutes, and administrative records that document Dingledine's work in the Social Studies and History Department at James Madison University (formerly Madison College), as well as correspondence and research materials for the book, "Madison College: the First Fifty Years, 1908-1958," authored by Dingledine and published in 1959.
Arrangement
Items are arranged into two series, and are further arranged by subject matter. Series 1: Research Files, 1956-1958 Series 2: Topical Files, 1950-1983
Related Materials
Dingledine, Raymond C., Jr. "Madison College: the First Fifty Years, 1908-1958." Harrisonburg, VA: Madison College, 1959.
Bibliography
Find A Grave. "Raymond C. Dingledine, Jr. (1919-1990)." Find a Grave Memorial no. 176163788. Accessed March 26, 2018. https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/ 176163788.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- History; James Madison University. Department of History; Dingledine, Raymond C., Jr. -- 1919-1990; Madison College. Department of History; Education, Higher -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Minutes (administrative records); Research notes; Pamphlets; Administrative reports
- Research Files, 1956-1958
  Scope and Contents
  Research Papers, 1956-1958, includes correspondence related to Dingledine's research for the book, "Madison College: the First Fifty Years, 1908-1958," published in 1959. It is largely comprised of reflections by alumnae of the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Harrisonburg (later known as State Normal School for Women) about their experiences of campus life from 1909 until ca. 1925. Notable contributors include Rachel Cleveland Ebbert Burruss and Linnie Lucille Campbell Duke, and Harry Foster, Secretary of the State Board of Education regarding minutes of the Virginia Normal School Board and State Teacher College Board held in Richmond (1:1). The series includes a pamphlet and order form announcing the release of the book (1:2).
  - Correspondence Re: "Madison College, the First Fifty Years", 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Re: "Madison College, the First Fifty Years", 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Topical Files, 1950-1983
  Scope and Content
  Series 2: Topical Files, 1950-1983, is comprised of professional and academic papers maintained by Dr. Dingledine in his capacity as professor within the History Department at Madison College. Note that the file, "Faculty Judiciary Committee, 1970" (2:8) is restricted due to FERPA.
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study College Curriculum, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Basic Studies Committee, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Basic Studies Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Basic Studies Committee, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bicentennial of the American Revolution, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - College Judicial Appeals Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - College Judicial Council, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee for the Development of High Technology, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Curriculum and Instruction, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Curriculum and Instruction, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Curriculum and Instruction, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Faculty Recruiting Policy, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee on University Academic and Research Collections, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Evaluation Policies, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Salary Scales, 1965-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Founders Day Lecture by Dr. Merrill D. Peterson, March 19, 1976
    - Original audiocassette, March 19, 1976 (Box 1, Audiocassette UA0037-CS-003)
  - General Education (Basic Studies), 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Godwin Hall Dedication, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - In-Service Teacher Education Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - James Madison Leadership Society, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Judicial Reform Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Major-Minor Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Master/Apprentice Program, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pass-Fail System, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Professional Development Committee, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - School of Communication Study Committee, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - School of Social Sciences, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 75th Anniversary Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sixth Year Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Social Science and History Department, 1957-1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Social Studies Certification Requirements, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools Library Study Committee, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools Self-Study, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - A History of JMU: a talk given by Raymond Dingledine, April 21, 1983
    Talk given for the Wayland and Phi Alpha Theta organizations. Recorded by Martha Caldwell.
    - Original audiocassette, April 21, 1983 (Box 1, Audiocassette UA0037-CS-001)
    - Preservation master, April 21, 1983 (Box 1, Audiocassette UA0037-CS-002)
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 21, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)